Guide to the Cedric N. Chatterley Photographs, 1983-2013 and undated RL.00219
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- David "Honeyboy" Edwards Series, 1990-1996 and undated, 4 boxes; 119 prints
  - S. Rampart Street (the apartments where Honeyboy lived for a short time are now gone - they were just the other side of the two-story building). New Orleans, Louisiana, 1993 March (Box 17)
  - Holding room in Avoyelles Parish Courthouse, Marksville, Louisiana (birthplace of Honeyboy's good friend "Little Walter" or Marion Jacobs, 1993 March (Box 17)
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards after performing at the Chicago Blues Festival, 1993 June (Box 17)
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards at his 78th birthday party - Rosa's Lounge, Chicago, Illinois - 4th of July weekend, 1993. (Box 17)
  - Stairwell, Aberdeen, Mississippi, 1993 October (Box 17)
  - Sweet Home Missionary Baptist Church (Honeyboy's childhood church) near Money, Mississippi, 1993 October (Box 17)
  - Closed department store, downtown Helena, Arkansas, 1993 October (Box 17)
  - Alley outside the Hole in the Wall bar in downtown Helena, Arkansas. This is where Honeyboy and his future wife, Bessie, had their first conversation. 1993 Oct. (Box 17)
  - Watching Honeyboy from inside his front room window on S. Wells Street. (Honeyboy's Lincoln is in the frame.) Near 43rd, Southside Chicago, 1994 Winter (Box 17)
  - Alice Edwards, Honeyboy's sister-in-law, holding the only existing photograph of Honeyboy's mother, Pearl Edwards. Chicago, Illinois, 1994 Winter (Box 17)
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards (seated) surrounded by his extended family (at his sister-in-law's house - Alice Edwards). Chicago, Illinois, 1994 Winter (Box 17)
  - Parting ways after the family portrait session, in front of Honeyboy's sister-in-law's place (Alice Edwards). Honeyboy's son, David, is waving. He would pass away two years later. Chicago, Illinois, 1994 Winter (Box 17)
  - Man walking, Southside Chicago (47th Street), 1994 Winter (Box 17)
  - Wig store, Southside Chicago (Halstead Street), 1994 Winter (Box 17)
  - Parking lot for fish store on Chicago's Southside. The truck comes up from Mississippi and other states with live fish, 1994 Winter (Box 17)
  - Mississippi River, Memphis, Tennessee, 1994 Winter (Box 17)
  - Just south of Houston's downtown (5th ward), Texas, 1994 Spring (Box 17)
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards holding a t-shirt - to be signed for a fan - for Albert "Sunnyland Slim" Luandrew at the the Chicago Blues Festival, 1994 June (Box 17)
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards at Chicago Blues Festival, 1994 June (Box 17)
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards cousin, Willie Mae Powell, for whom Robert Johnson wrote "Love in Vain." She and Robert Johnson dated off and on before his death. Her front yard, outside Tunica, Mississippi, 1994 October (Box 17)
  - Honeyboy's cousin, Willie Mae Powell, laughing in her front yard. She dated Robert Johnson for a period of time. Outside Tunica, Mississippi, 1994 October (Box 17)
  - Child's tomb next to Sweet Home Missionary Baptist Church near Money, Mississippi, 1994 October (Box 17)
  - Cotton harvest near Money, Mississippi, 1994 October (Box 17)
  - Cotton harvest near Money, Mississippi, 1994 October (Box 17)
  - Just outside the long-closed Hole in the Wall bar, downtown Helena, Arkansas, 1994 October (Box 18)
  - Honeyboy at the King Biscuit Blues Festival. Helena, Arkansas, 1994 October (Box 18)
  - Big Bad Smitty (John H. Smith) playing guitar in Eddie's Tavern, downtown Helena, Arkansas, about an hour following the closing of the King Biscuit Blues Festival, 1994 October (Box 18)
  - Looking through glass of cafe on Oretha Castle Haley Blvd., New Orleans, Louisiana, 1994 October (Box 18)
  - Abandoned church, Memphis, Tennessee, 1994 (Box 18)
  - Near Barlow, Kentucky, heading towards Cairo, Illinois, 1995 Winter (Box 18)
  - Heading north on Highway 51 - leaving Mounds, Illinois, 1995 Winter (Box 18)
  - Apparatus used to engrave stone gravesite memorials. Bell Monuments, Cairo, Illinois, 1995 Winter (Box 18)
  - Abandoned meat packing plant, Southside Chicago, 1995 Winter (Box 18)
  - Amtrak passing through Chicago's Southside, heading north, 1995 Winter (Box 18)
  - Friends jamming. South 47th Street storefront, Chicago, Illinois, 1995 Winter (Box 18)
  - Man selling cassette tapes, South 47th Street, Chicago, Illinois, 1995 Winter (Box 18)
  - (Image of Jesus) Southside Chicago, 1995 Winter (Box 18)
  - Honeyboy's young friend, Charles, whom he often watched after, sitting in the kitchen with a guitar Honeyboy had given him. On Wells Street, near 43rd, Southside Chicago, 1995 Winter (Box 18)
  - Man mowing, New Orleans, Louisiana, 1995 Spring (Box 18)
  - Birthplace of David "Honeyboy" Edwards. His childhood home, long ago destroyed and plowed under, once stood in this field outside Shaw, Mississippi, 1995 Spring (Box 18)
  - Warehouse District - just south of downtown Memphis, Tennessee, 1995 May (Box 18)
  - Memphis - from atop the train station, looking north/northwest, 1995 May (Box 18)
  - Memphis train station, long closed, 1995 May (Box 18)
  - Painting, downtown Caruthersville, Missouri, 1995 May (Box 18)
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards descending staircase of a bed and breakfast in Derby, England, 1996 Fall (Box 18)
  - David "Honeyboy" Edwards backstage in the Wakefield Theatre, Wakefield, England, 1996 Fall (Box 18)
  - Untitled/undated print of David "Honeyboy" Edwards with another man. Honeyboy is holding a RC Cola bottle (Box 18)
  - Untitled/undated print of David "Honeyboy" Edwards laughing with another man while leaning on the hood of a car (Box 18)
  - Five untitled/undated contact prints of David "Honeyboy" Edwards (Box 18)
  - Untitled/undated print of David "Honeyboy" Edwards with family at Alice Edwards's house (Box 18)
- Spencer, South Dakota Series, 1998-2008, 7 boxes; 268 prints
  This large body of work consists of images documenting the aftermath of a powerful tornado that caused the nearly total destruction of Spencer, South Dakota (McCook County) by a tornado on May 30, 1998, as well as the subsequent rebuilding of the town, and the tenth anniversary of the tornado. The photographer, Cedric Chatterly, is a resident of South Dakota. Original captions are taken from back of prints. The 268 gelatin silver prints are arranged in original order as received, with some gaps in numbering present.
  - 11x14 gelatin silver selenium-toned prints, 192 prints
    - Jenny Phillips with her cat who was miraculously saved after the tornado, May 1998 (Box 19, Print 1)
      This is one of the very first photographs I made when I arrived a half a mile north of Spencer on May 31, 1998. People were gethering on the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431. A state police barricade would stop many people from entering, including residents. I entered easier than most with my Press Pass. Governor Bill Janklow was there giving the "go ahead" to anybody wanting to board the bus.
    - Entering Spencer by way of Department of Corrections bus the day following the tornado, May 1998 (Box 19, Print 2)
    - Christ figure atop the remains of St. Matthews Lutheran Church in Spencer, May 1998 (Box 19, Print 3)
      F-4 tornado hit the town around 8:30 pm, May 30, 1998.
    - Department of Corrections inmate gathering remains of Evelyn's Antiques the day following the tornado in Spencer, May 1998 (Box 19, Print 4)
    - Apartments (left) where elderly people died in the tornado & across the street from the apartments (right), Spencer, May 1998 (Box 19, Print 5)
      This print was made from two negatives printed consecutively.
    - Crews removing damaged trees in the aftermath of the F-4, May 30th tornado, Spencer, June 1998 (Box 19, Print 6)
    - Scattered clothing found on the east side of Spencer two days following the tornado, June 1998 (Box 19, Print 7)
    - Men standing where there had been a water tower (left) and rolling down the road headed north on a four-wheeler just outside of Spencer, June 1998 (Box 19, Print 8)
      A kid on a four-wheeler wanted to show Chatterley where a circular saw blade had stuck itself into a tree. This print was made from two negatives printed consecutively.
    - Newscaster at live broadcast in Spencer, June 1998 (Box 19, Print 9)
    - Kara Arends and Danny Stone looking at a few of their recovered belongings three days after the F-4 tornado. Danny's pickup is upside down on the right side of the image. Both of them were at home at the time with one month old Brandon, their son, June 1998 (Box 19, Print 10)
    - Jenna Webb and Cliff Carlin in the house in Spencer where Jenna's grandmother lived at the time of her passing, June 1998 (Box 19, Print 11)
      Cliff had lived in this house for six months and had considered buying it from the Webbs. The mud on the walls of the house was caused by the water tower falling to the ground during the tornado.
    - Before the big news conference held on June 3, 1998 in Spencer (Box 19, Print 12)
      Among those present are Governor Bill Janklow, Senator Tom Daschle, Senator Tim Johnson, FEMA Director James Lee Witt, and Vice President Al Gore.
    - Milford Hickman, Division Commander for the Salvation Army, being congradulated by Vice President Al Gore in Spencer, July 1998 (Box 19, Print 13)
    - Boy running in downtown Spencer, July 1998 (Box 19, Print 14)
    - Donated bread and clothing for tornado survivors at the National Guard Armory in Salem, South Dakota, July 1998 (Box 19, Print 15)
    - June 4, 1998 - the day nearly 5,000 volunteers came to Spencer to help "comb" the entire town for valuables, clothing, tools, and anything that had not already been picked up (Box 19, Print 16)
      Governor Bill Janklow asked for 500 volunteers through media outlets just days prior to this event. A F-4 tornado came through Spencer around 8:30 on May 30, 1998, destroying nearly 75% of a town with 325 people. Only six people were killed.
    - June 4, 1998 - the day 5-6 thousand people volunteered to "comb" Spencer, South Dakota for valuables, etc (Box 19, Print 17)
    - Tables of donated desserts (sandwiches are on other tables) to feed the 5-6 thousand volunteers who showed up to "comb" Spencer on June 4, 1998 (Box 19, Print 18)
    - Lloyd Webb unloading furniture that had been in storage in a friend's barn at the Webb's farmhouse, McCook County, South Dakota, January 1999 (Box 19, Print 111)
    - Workers rebuilding the tornado-destroyed bank in Spencer, January 1999 (Box 19, Print 112)
      It was snowing and the windchill was around 25 degrees below zero.
    - Mary Twedt painting trim in the second bathroom at the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota (about 1/2 mile south of Spencer), January 1999 (Box 19, Print 113)
    - Lloyd Webb about to load hay into his pickup in the north pasture not far from the farm house (3 miles north of Spencer) and me in my studio darkroom in downtown Sioux Falls, South Dakota, January 1999 (Box 19, Print 114)
      I rented this studio space from August 1997 to March 2007. This print was made from two negatives printed consecutively.
    - Mary Twedt in the passenger seat of the Dodge van, with Dave and me on the way to Mitchell, South Dakota to pick up building materials, South Dakota Highway 38, February 1999 (Box 19, Print 115)
    - Danny Stone attaching a canvas to his house in Spencer, February 1999 (Box 19, Print 116)
      Danny is the main canvas sewing employee at Spencer Canvas in Mitchell, South Dakota. He designed and made all the awning for his house.
    - Lloyd Webb and me looking for a lost calf about three miles north of Spencer, February 1999 (Box 19, Print 117)
    - Lloyd Webb putting down a cow that had major problems following the still-birth of a calf the night before, Valentine's Day, 2000 (Box 19, Print 118)
      This was the day (ironically) that we rounded up the last of the cattle on Webb's farm, putting an end to three generations of having cattle on this land. The dead calf was close by and the mother cow was nearly dead at the time of this shooting. It was 15 degrees and windy.
      This print was made from three negatives printed consecutively.
    - Mother cow after Lloyd Webb put her down (hole in skull). (Box 19, Print 119)
      Her calf is twelve feet away (left). Complications arose the night before while giving birth in the north pasture. Ironically, this was the day Lloyd and I rounded up the remaining cattle for market, leaving the Webb's land free of beef -- only about twenty horses remained. Valentine's Day, February 14, 2000. McCook County, South Dakota.
    - Lloyd Webb (right) and a neighbor herd the very last cows to a trailer to take to market, three miles north of Spencer, Valentine's Day, 2000 (Box 19, Print 120)
      They were among the 25 or 30 that remained on Lloyd and Nancy Webb's farm, thus ending the bovine legacy that began with her father. Nancy refused to help because she was too emotional about this event.
    - The west side of Lloyd and Nancy Webb's farmhouse that is part of a new addition, McCook County, South Dakota, 3 miles north of Spencer, March 1999 (Box 19, Print 122)
    - Lloyd Webb storing a rock-hard (frozen) roll of Linoleum in the barn, McCook County, South Dakota, 3 miles north of Spencer at the family farm, February 1999 (Box 19, Print 123)
    - Lloyd and Suzy Webb filling the 1950 Chevy with gas in Spencer, March 1999 (Box 19, Print 124)
      Lloyd will buy a 1952 Chevy later in the year. He had a 1953 Chevy heavily damaged in the tornado and regrettably let Bernie Opland crush it and haul it off.
    - Lloyd Webb loading corn to feed the horses while Richard Nixon, the little dog, watches at the barn across from the farmhouse, McCook County, 3 miles north of Spencer, March 1999 (Box 19, Print 125)
    - Tim DeWitt motioning to Steve Tillotson (below, Nancy Webb's brother) while he and Lloyd Webb (hand at right) set roofing joyces on Steve's house in West Spencer, March 1999 (Box 19, Print 126)
    - Danny Stone being interviewed by local television crew in McCook County, South Dakota, March 1999 (Box 19, Print 127)
      This was pertaining to his contractor abandoning the Stone's home construction in Spencer and leaving them $35,000 in debt. A court settlement was finally reached but the Stones filed for bankruptcy a few years later.
    - Dave and Mary Twedt out by the barn pile with their new pet, Sasha, near the intersection of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota, March 1999 (Box 19, Print 128)
    - Dave Twedt laying carpet in the living room, about 1/2 mile North of Spencer, April, 1999 (Box 19, Print 129)
      This building had once been the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and it was connected to several motor lodges. Dave bought their home in Spencer around 1990.
    - Mary Twedt with a quilt she made in anticipation of the birth of her first grandchild (Kaitlyn Ann), May, 1999 (Box 19, Print 130)
    - Nancy Stone and Richard Stone planting trees near Danny's house in Spencer, May 1999 (Box 19, Print 131)
      Richard had been living with friends or relatives and coming and ging from Spencer. He is now 17 and thinking of leaving school.
    - Danny Stone (left) and Richard Stone putting up a clothes line not long after celebrating Brandon's 1st birthday, Spencer, May 1999 (Box 19, Print 132)
    - Lloyd Webb setting up two mailboxes in front of the farmhouse on 249th street, McCook County, South Dakota, May 1999 (Box 19, Print 133)
      One box was for him and Nancy and the other was for their daughter Jenna. The mail carrier could not come down this road unless there was more than one mailbox, although Jenna only lived part-time at the farm.
    - Local priests, Catholic officials and altar boys prepare to dedicate the Catholic Parish Center in Spencer on May 30, 1999 (Box 19, Print 134)
      This had been the location of St. Mary's Catholic Church, which was destroyed by the May 30 tornado.
    - Suzy Webb watching Nancy Webb demonstrate standing on one's head one year and one day following the tornado, May 1999 (Box 19, Print 135)
      Bridgette looks on. They are in the north pasture about 1/4 mile from their farmhouse. Nancy's grandfather homesteaded this acreage.
    - Brandon Stone and his father Danny, one year and one day after the Spencer tornado, May 1999 (Box 19, Print 136)
    - Danny and Brandon Stone preparing to pour concrete for the front walk and steps one year and one day after the F-4 tornado took their home, Spencer, May 1999 (Box 19, Print 137)
    - Opening of the Trinity Lutheran Church, Spencer, June 1999 (Box 19, Print 138)
      The church was rebuilt during the years that followed the tornado. The woman in the right image is holding an Argus Leader newsprint, published the day after the May 30 tornado.
    - Richard Stone (right) and his friend Wendy hanging out in front of the Word of Life Church in Mitchell, South Dakota, June 1999 (Box 19, Print 139)
      The youth minister at this church would let kids come and go and Richard was basically a runaway at this time.
    - Danny Stone and Brandon taking a cruise through Spencer shortly after the water tower was completed, July 1999 (Box 19, Print 140)
    - Richard Stone mowing his dad's yard (Danny Stone), Spencer, July 1999 (Box 19, Print 141)
      Richard has returned home after being away for several weeks living on the streets and staying with friends in Mitchell, South Dakota.
    - Mary Twedt (left) and her daughter, Jessica, out behind the commercial property they are building into a home about a half mile south of Spencer on the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, June 1999 (Box 19, Print 142)
      Jessica is nearly 9 months pregnant with her first born Kaitlyn Ann.
    - Mary Twedt in the garden she and Dave planted on the corner of South Dakota Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota, June 1999 (Box 19, Print 143)
      This is directly in front of the closed motor lodge rooms on the commercial property they are making into a home. Dave is planning to start a herb and vegetable business called "Asphalt Gardens."
    - Tim Dewitt (with hanging sunglasses) and Richard Stone viewing the "Spencer" exhibit at the Washington Pavillion of Arts and Science in Sioux Falls, South Dakota less than one block from my studio darkroom, June 1999 (Box 19, Print 144)
    - Richard Stone watches while Tim Dewitt cut a hole for car speakers in his 1968 Ford Maverick, behind Richard's uncle's house in Spencer, June 1999 (Box 20, Print 145)
    - Richard Stone and Tim Dewitt on Country Road 431 heading south towards Spencer, McCook County, South Dakota, June 1999 (Box 20, Print 146)
    - Jayson Fredricks holding Kaitlyn Ann the day she was born in Sioux Valley Hospital, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, July 19, 1999 (Box 20, Print 147)
    - Lloyd Webb and me riding in the north pasture about 1/2 mile from the farmhouse, McCook County, South Dakota, 3 miles north of Spencer, August 1999 (Box 20, Print 148)
    - Tim Dewitt (standing) and Lloyd Webb about to remove an axle from a truck rear end, near the barn at the Webb's farmhouse, 3 miles north of Spencer, Labor Day Weekend, 1998 (Box 20, Print 149)
    - Isaac Carlin, son of Jenna Webb Carlin and Cliff Carlin, playing on the floor at Lloyd and Nancy's, 3 mies north of Spencer, McCook County, South Dakota, Labor Day Weekend, 1999 (Box 20, Print 150)
      There were several birthdays in the Webb/Tilotson clan celebrated that day (Suzy, Jenna, and Myrta).
    - Tim Dewitt and Richard Stone working late on a Chevrolet Chevette in front of Steve Tillotson's place in West Spencer, South Dakota, late summer 1999 (Box 20, Print 151)
      Steve is Nancy Webb's brother.
    - Tim Dewitt pulling a transmission from an early 1980s Chevy in Steve Tillotson's "junkyard" in West Spencer, October 1999 (Box 20, Print 152)
      Steve is Nancy Webb's brother and the boyfriend of Maggie, Tim's mother.
    - Lloyd Webb in his truck with Nancy's dog Richard Nixon perched on his favorite riding place, at the north pasture on the Webbs' farm, November 1999 (Box 20, Print 153)
      Nixon got his name because he was born in a milkhouse. At first, he was called Milkhouse, which quickly turned to Millhouse, which quickly turned into Richard Nixon. I ran over Richard Nixon when the dog came running out to greet me at Lloyd's birthday party in late March 1999. Lloyd and I took him to the vet in Salem, got him fixed up and returned to the farm to finish the party. They made a pen in the house to keep Richard Nixon from running.
    - Richard Stone out behind the Webbs' barn moving old farm machinery and doing some general clean-up, McCook County, 3 miles north of Spencer, late fall 1999 (Box 20, Print 154)
    - Suzy and Lloyd Webb in the 1952 Chevy heading north on County Road 431, passing an abandoned farmhouse between Spencer and the Webbs' farm, December 1999 (Box 20, Print 155)
    - Lloyd Webb showing Nancy his custom gift-wrapping of a cat-like figure about one week before Christmas, McCook County, 3 miles north of Spencer in the family farmhouse, December 1999 (Box 20, Print 156)
      The gift was for Myrta, Nancy's sister. Mama cat is in the bottom center.
    - Lloyd, Suzy and Nancy Webb examining the new gun/rifle safe, McCook County, 3 miles north of Spencer, Christmas Day, 1999 (Box 20, Print 157)
    - Suzy Webb with make-up kit at the family farmhouse, McCook County, 3 mies north of Spencer, Christmas Day, 1999 (Box 20, Print 158)
    - Richard Stone talking on the phone with a girlfriend, Western Avenue, near 10th street, January 2000 (Box 20, Print 159)
      He is staying part-time with his cousin in Sioux Falls, South Dakota.
    - Richard Stone and his father Danny Stone during a brief visit in Spencer, January 2000 (Box 20, Print 160)
      Richard is currently living with his aunt, Danny's sister, in Baltic, South Dakota.
    - Scattered jigsaw puzzle on the ground following the May 30 F-4 tornado, Spencer, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 19)
    - Workers salvaging grain from destroyed bins, Spencer, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 20)
    - National Guard and Department of Corrections personel working together gathering bags filled by the 5 thousand volunteers the day before, Spencer, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 21)
    - Crews (left) pushing and dumping razed buildings and homes from the tornado aftermath into one of two large pits. Bags (right) of itemes gathered by volunteers the day before that will be cleaned and taken to the McCook Central High School, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 22)
      The hogsed planter belonged to Dave and Mary Twedt. Ironically, this was before I met them. Weeks later, after meeting them, I went with them to McCook Central High School to retrieve items. They gave me the planter and I ended up giving it to my sister, Jolea.
    - Piled up household and domestic toxic material in downtown Spencer, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 23)
      Inmates from the South Dakota Department of Corrections were bussed out there every day to help with the clean-up.
    - Governor Bill Janklow talking to the media in downtown Spencer, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 24)
    - Broken crucifix from the tornado on a table atop the floor of the Trinity Lutheran Church, Spencer, June 1998 (Box 20, Print 25)
    - During the opening prayer at the Trinity Lutheran Church in Spencer, July 1998 (Box 20, Print 27)
      The chruch was destroyed by a tornado on May 30, 1998. This was the last service before a complete razing took place, preparing the way for a new chapel to be built. South Dakota Department of Corrections inmates gather. They had been instrumental in helping clean up efforts from the very beginning a week earlier.